(CREAKING AND SLAMMING)
(FAINT CLICKING)
(LOUD CLICK)
(INAUDIBLE)
MAN: What do you know, boys?
MAN 2: Hey, Papi,
get over here.
I got someone
I want you to meet.
Roland Legrand.
Caught this fucking goat singing
like a canary to the police.
Поймал этого ебучего козла,
когда он выкладывал всё полиции.
(GROANS)
This is what happens
when you cross me.
Вот что происходит,
когда идёшь против меня.
Get this piece of shit
out of here.
Уберите отсюда этот кусок говна.
So, what do you
got for me?
Итак, что у тебя есть для меня?
PAPILLON: Piece of cake,
just like you said.
Это было легко.
Как ты и говорил.
You pocket any
for yourself?
Себе тоже прикарманил?
Yeah, just a couple
of the big ones.
Ага, парочку крупных.
(LAUGHS)
You sure got
some balls on you.
А ты парень с яйцами.
You try to hustle me,
Попытаешься меня наебать,
and I'll cut them
the fuck off.
и я их отрежу к чёртовой матери.
MAN: Good for 10,000.
Тут на десять тысяч.
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
(DOOR OPENS AND SLAMS)
Did you have
a good night?
Хорошо провёл вечер?
- Yup.
- At least you did.
- Ага.
- Ну хоть ты отдохнул.
Maybe this'll
cheer you up.
Может, это поднимет тебе настроение?
Take it.
Возьми.
It's for you.
Это для тебя.
A couple of
the big ones for us.
А вот эти крупные - для нас.
You're crazy.
Where you going?
Castili doesn't want me
leaving early.
- Кастили не любит, когда я рано ухожу.
To hell with Castili.
К чёрту Кастили.
Let's go have some fun.
Давай повеселимся.
- Let's turn that frown upside down.
Заставим это хмурое личико улыбнуться.
I know you want
to have some fun.
Я знаю, ты хочешь повеселиться.
(HORN BLARES)
(LAUGHING)
WOMAN: I love you.
PAPILLON: Say that again.
Slower.
(WHISPERS) I...
...love...
...you.
I want a house.
In the countryside,
like where you grew up.
За городом,
как тот, в котором ты вырос.
You make it sound so nice,
riding our little horsey around.
Ты так славно рассказывал,
как катался вокруг него на лошадке.
Let's go today.
Давай уедем сегодня.
How am I going to earn
in the country?
Как я буду зарабатывать в деревне?
There's nothing to steal.
Там нечего красть.
We'll get jobs.
I made more last night
than most people in the
country make in a year.
Give me six months.
I'll be making more money
than Castili and all those bums.
(MUSIC STOPS)
Hey.
(SIGHS)
I don't want
to wait six months.
(KNOCKING)
WOMAN: I'm here for the rent.
Я пришла за оплатой.
(KNOCKING)
PAPILLON: All right.
I'm coming, I'm coming.
- POLICE OFFICER: It's him.
- What the fuck?
- Какого хуя?
You're under arrest for
the murder of Roland Legrand.
Вы арестованы
за убийство Ролана Леграна.
What are you
talking about?
Well, he was murdered
last night.
A witness
identified you.
Свидетель узнал вас.
The pimp Roland Legrand.
You know him, right?
Сутенёр,
Ролан Легран.
Вы знали его, верно?
You got the wrong guy, pal.
I was with her all night.
OFFICER: Come on. Let's go.
- All right, let me get dressed.
- No, no, no, no, no.
We got some stripes at the station
for you, pretty boy.
У нас в участке
есть костюмчик для тебя, красавчик.
- PAPILLON: This is bullshit.
- Cuff him.
I didn't kill anyone.
NENETTE: You can't do that.
- He was with me.
- PAPILLON: Nenette, relax.
- They got nothing.
- Nobody believes a whore.
- У них ничего нет.
- Никто не поверит шлюхе.
- Nenette!
- Get back in your room.
Honestly, I'll be back
in no time.
- Papi! Papi!
- Don't worry. Don't worry.
Papi!
He didn't kill anyone!
He was with me!
(DOOR SLAMS AND LOCKS)
OFFICER:
Step away from the bars.
Отойти от решётки!
NENETTE: I can't believe
they gave you a life sentence.
Не верю, что они
приговорили тебя к пожизненному.
You need to appeal.
Ты должен обжаловать это.
Appeal what?
Nenette,
this is a frame-up.
Наннет, меня подставили.
They're all in on it.
Они всё замешаны.
I just need to concentrate
on breaking out.
Я должен сконцентрироваться на побеге.
Okay.
First thing I'm going
to do when I get back
И первым делом после возвращения
is kill that lying
rat witness
я убью эту лживую крысу-свидетеля
and anyone who has
anything to do with this.
и каждого, кто имел к этому отношение.
Calm down.
- Успокойся.
OFFICER:
All visitors have to leave.
Nenette, you need
to forget about me.
Don't say that.
I love you.
OFFICER: Time's up, lady.
Papi, I love you.
Come on.
Come on. Come on.
- Get your hands off me!
- Come on. Come on.
- Убери от меня руки!
(KICKS BARS)
(CLANGING)
Papillon, right?
They fucked you good, huh?
Они неплохо тебя отделали.
Framed you for murder.
Подставили за убийство.
Say you're one hell
of a safe cracker.
Говорят, ты чертовски
хороший медвежатник.
I'm more of a smash-and-grab guy myself.
Name's Julot.
Я больше по части
разбойных нападений. Я Джуло.
Got any money?
No?
Get some.
You'll never escape without it.
OFFICER: All right. Let's go.
Let's keep going.
OFFICER 2: Next. Move forward.
OFFICER: Next. Come on.
OFFICER 3: Line five.
OFFICER: Let's go, let's go.
OFFICER 4: Move.
OFFICER 3: Next.
OFFICER: Next.
OFFICER 5: Line up.
OFFICER 3: Go to the end.
OFFICER 2: Come on. Move along.
(COUGHS)
- OFFICER 3: Stay in line.
- Hey.
Perhaps I could speak
with your supervisor.
Возможно, мне стоит
поговорить с твоим надзирателем.
Sure. Whatever you say.
Louis Dega.
Guy's a millionaire.
Busted making counterfeit
defense bonds.
Попался на изготовлении
поддельных оборонных облигаций.
- All right. Next.
- Won't last long.
Every con in the prison
will want to cut him open
Каждый в этой тюрьме захочет вскрыть его,
чтобы найти спрятанные деньги.
to get the money
he's carrying.
GUARD: Next.
MAN: As of this moment,
you are the property
of the penal administration
of French Guiana.
After serving your full term
in prison,
После отбытия полного срока
you will remain in South America
as workers and colonists
вы останетесь в Южной Америке
в качестве рабочих и колонистов
на срок, равный вашему приговору.
for a period equal to that
of your original sentence.
This is for the greater good
that is French expansion.
Это великое благо
для расширения Франции.
As for France,
А что касается Франции,
she has disowned you.
она от вас отказалась.
She has rid herself
of you altogether.
на избавила себя от…всех вас.
Forget France.
Now dress yourself.
- I'm going to hell.
- God, please. Keep walking.
LAWYER: Mr. Dega.
Your appeal is
in a few weeks.
Ваша апелляция будет через пару недель.
Be strong, Louis.
I love you.
You'll be home
before Christmas.
MAN: Dega. Mr. Dega, here.
Look this way.
Mr. Dega.
GUARD:...69, 70.
GUARD 2: Move it.
GUARD 3: That's enough.
GUARD 4: Pick your feet up.
(SHOUTING AND CLAMORING)
Hey, Julot.
GUARD: All right, pair up.
PAPILLON:
Hey, take the corner.
(INAUDIBLE)
JULOT: Looks like Dega's
making friends already.
Похоже, Дега уже завёл себе друзей.
Julot, make sure no one
takes this hammock.
Джуло, проследи,
чтобы никто не занял этот гамак.
MAN: What are you looking at?
PAPILLON: Hey.
I saved you a spot
next to me.
You got a lot
of eyes on you.
На тебя все пялятся.
I can keep you safe.
All I need's enough money
for an escape.
Всё, что мне надо,
это деньги для побега.
Won't be cheap,
but you'll be safe.
Будет недёшево,
зато ты в безопасности.
Said the scorpion
to the frog.
Сказал скорпион лягушке.
We're all scorpions
in here, pal.
I think I'd be better off
taking my chances
Я думаю, мне стоит
.лучше держаться ближе к охране.
setting up in front of the
guards, wouldn't you agree?
You seem like the kind of man
who can make up his own mind.
You're a good judge
of character.
А ты хорошо разбираешься в людях.
Have a good night.
Yeah, you, too.
Hey. Me and you,
we should team up for an escape.
If I get caught in some half-assed escape,
I want it to be my mistake.
Если меня поймают посреди дурацкого побега,
я хочу, чтобы это было моей ошибкой.
(HORN BLOWS)
GUARD: Settle down, now.
(MAN 1 SHUSHES)
- (MUFFLED SCREAMING)
- (SWITCHBLADE OPENS)
- (STABBING)
- (MAN 1 GRUNTING)
(MUFFLED SCREAMING
INTENSIFIES)
(SCREAMING STOPS)
MAN 1: I know you hide
your money in your guts.
Я знаю, что ты прячешь
деньги в своих кишках.
(WHISTLE BLOWING)
GUARD: Upper deck.
Верхняя палуба.
Move it back. Back, you.
Back. Back now.
Get him out of here.
The animals can clean up
their own mess.
Эти животные
могут сами убрать за собой.
Come on. Get rid of him.
Давайте. Избавьтесь от него.
GUARD 2: Show's over.
(DOOR SLAMS AND LOCKS)
How'd you sleep
last night?
Smells like freedom.
What,
you've heard of someone escaping the prison?
А ты что, слышал,
чтобы кто-то сбежал из тюрьмы?
Doesn't mean
it can't be done.
Это не значит, что это невозможно.
I have trouble seeing hope
in hopelessness.
У меня проблемы с поиском
надежды в безнадёге.
That's why I need
a man like you.
Поэтому мне нужен
такой человек, как ты.
I've reconsidered
your offer.
Я ещё раз обдумал твоё предложение.
You keep me alive until
I'm set up on the island,
Помоги мне остаться в живых,
пока мы не устроимся на острове,
I'll underwrite any escape
you care to arrange.
а я покрываю любой побег,
который ты организуешь.
All right.
And when the time comes,
you're not coming with me.
И когда придёт время,
ты со мной не пойдёшь.
I have no intention
of escaping.
У меня нет намерений сбегать.
Unlike you,
I enjoy being alive.
В отличие от тебя,
мне нравится быть живым.
My wife's working
on my appeal.
I'm confident
I'll be home by Christmas.
A fellow optimist.
GUARD: I'm in for one.
GUARD 2: Two.
(YELLS)
MAN: Look what the fuck
you did!
Ты что, блядь, натворил!
(CLAMORING)
MAN 2: Yeah!
PAPILLON: Get the knife.
Come on! Get the knife!
Get the knife!
- (CLAMORING INTENSIFIES)
- (WHISTLES BLOWING)
(ALL SHOUTING)
I'll kill you!
GUARD: Steam!
GUARD 2: Turn on the steam!
Пар! Включите пар!
(WHISTLE BLOWING)
(STEAM HISSING, ALL GROANING)
(SCREAMING)
(GROANING)
GUARD: Come on,
come on, come on.
(BLOWING WHISTLE)
GUARD 2: Get back!
GUARD: Strip and line up,
you fucking animals, or it's the steam again.
аздевайтесь и вставайте в линию,
ёбаные животные, или снова включу пар.
- All right, on your feet. Strip down.
- (TRUNCHEONS BANGING)
JULOT: Give me
the fucking knife.
GUARD: Move it. Come on.
Line up in back there.
Let's go. Strip down.
Come on. Come on.
On your feet.
Line up in back there.
Strip down. Strip right up.
Hands. Hands out.
Everybody, hands out.
GUARD 2: Everyone, let's have
your hands out. Let's see.
What you got?
GUARD 3: Get him to the infirmary.
All right, let's get
this piece of meat out of here.
Show me your hands. Let's see.
Turn them over. You.
Yeah, this one's
been fighting for sure.
- Take him to first class.
- Come on.
Come on.
Time to go.
First class, let's go.
Try and behave, ladies.
(DOOR OPENS AND CREAKS)
(GRUNTING)
GUARD: Go!
JULOT:
You should've finished him.
I don't want
to kill anyone.
I'm going to get myself
sent to the hospital.
Хочу, чтобы меня отправили в госпиталь.
Let me know if a guard
looks this way.
Дай мне знать,
если охрана будет смотреть.
GUARD: Do not stop!
GUARD 2: Get a move along!
- Eyes front!
- (JULOT SHUSHING)
(GROANING)
GUARD: Move it. Now! You, too.
Let's go! You heard me.
- Move it! Move it!
- Crazy, Julot.
GUARD: Go that way.
You go this way.
You two. Come on now.
Form a line.
I said form a line. Go ahead.
You two. You stay here.
Go back in line.
Move it! Come on. That way.
- Come on, move it. Come on.
- Move. Move along.
I said move it, God damn it.
Get up! Get up!
Come on, you. Move along.
Move along.
Eyes straight. Eyes straight.
Come on. Move.
That way. Over there. Come on.
GUARD: Faster!
GUARD 2: Move! Move it!
GUARD: Come on now!
GUARD 2: Come on, move.
GUARD: Don't be looking at me
like that.
GUARD 2: Come on, move!
GUARD: You, too.
Move along.
- (THUD)
- (JULOT SCREAMING)
All right! Get him up!
JULOT: My fucking leg!
(JULOT SCREAMING)
My leg.
My leg!
(JULOT SCREAMING)
GUARD: That's enough.
- Break it up. Break it up.
- Move back. Move back.
- Get in line!
Move. Back to the line.
Move. Move.
GUARD: Raise your hand
if I call your name.
Augustin.
Barba.
GUARD 2: Come on, now.
Stay in line.
GUARD: Bellaire.
GUARD 3: Move along.
Over there.
GUARD: Lofton.
GUARD 3: Form straight
up over there.
GUARD: Navarrone.
Navarrone.
GUARD 4: Move out!
GUARD 3: Move out!
(TROPICAL BIRDS SCREECH)
GUARD: All right.
Come on. Move it.
Keep moving!
Prisoners, halt!
Open the gates.
March!
I know many of you at this very
moment are thinking about escape.
Feel free to try
whenever you like.
Можете пробовать, когда вам вздумается.
We'll be happy to shoot you.
If, however,
you should avoid that mercy,
there are two guardians
who are always on duty.
The bush, where the best thing that
can happen to you is starvation.
Заросли, где лучшее, что с вами
может случиться - это голодная смерть.
Or you could choose the sea,
where sharks, too, I assure you,
are always hungry.
If you manage to survive
your first attempt,
you'll get two years
in solitary.
вас ждут два года в одиночной камере.
Second attempt,
five years in solitary
followed by a life sentence
at Devils Island.
за которыми последует
пожизненное заключение на острове Дьявола.
If you commit murder,
you'll be executed.
вас казнят.
That's all.
(MEN SHOUTING)
Move, move!
(WHISTLE BLOWING)
Jesus Christ.
Here. Take the corner.
Hey. Keep your eyes open
and don't move.
Hey.
Who decides what work
we get assigned to?
(CHUCKLING)
- Excuse my ill-mannered...
- I thought I told you not to move.
- Извините моего бестактного…
- Я вроде бы сказал тебе не двигаться.
He has yet to be tamed.
Его ещё предстоит обучить манерам.
And you're obviously a very important,
very, very busy man.
I'm just a turnkey.
Я просто надзиратель.
We're looking for
someone to ensure
Мы ищем кого-то,
кто бы гарантировал нам,
we're assigned the right
sort of work in the morning.
что с утра нас запишут
на подходящую работу.
It'll cost you 1,000.
I don't think so.
No. Now that seems
entirely too high.
Нет, сейчас эта цена
кажется слишком завышенной.
Sir.
I think we started off
on the wrong foot.
Сэр, мы неправильно начали нашу беседу.
I think 1,000
is actually fair.
Вообще, думаю,
тысяча - это довольно честно.
Now, is there a selection
of work you have?
А теперь, есть ли у вас
перечень работы…
Attendants at
the hospital.
And for a thousand you can
throw in a pouch of tobacco.
И за тысячу можешь
ещё накинуть немного табака.
- And a notebook.
- A notebook?
- I'm an artist.
- You're a forger.
- Я художник.
- Ты фальшивомонетчик.
And you're
a safe cracker,
А ты взломщик сейфов,
a profession of which
I thoroughly disapprove.
и это профессия,
которую я искренне не одобряю.
At least I'm
an honest criminal.
По крайней мере,
я честный преступник.
Hey, I'm gonna
need that right now.
- I mean, right now.
- Excuse me.
I think you need
to go to the bathroom.
Yes, of course.
If you'll excuse me,
gentlemen.
Where are you going?
I've never
been here before.
Toilet's there,
princess.
What animal but a man
keeps his only means
of survival up his ass?
Кто ещё кроме человека будет держать единственную
жизненно важную вещь у себя в заднице?
- (FLIES BUZZING)
- (SIGHS)
(GRUNTING)
Something bit me.
- (SQUEAKING)
- (WINGS FLUTTERING)
(DOG BARKING)
(GUN SHOT)
(GUNFIRE)
- GUARD: We got a runner!
- (ALARM BLARING)
Lockdown!
GUARD 2: Lock it down.
MAN: Which barracks?
MAN 2: No, he broke out of the hospital.
- Just one, I think.
- The hospital?
Lock down your barrack!
I bet that's Julot.
GUARD: Lock it down!
PAPILLON: Son of a bitch
didn't waste any time.
- GUARD: Lock down the north barrack!
- (GUNFIRE)
PAPILLON: You see?
It can be done.
GUARD: Lock it down.
Into the jungle. Stand down.
MAN: Route zero.
Route zero.
My friend and I need to be
kept together at all times.
Set these two up
in the hospital.
Этих двоих в госпиталь.
And it'll be a few days before
I'm well enough to do any...
- Don't push it.
- ...work.
Route zero.
MAN: Mr. Dega. Stop.
I know you.
Do you know me?
Yes. Yes,
of course.
You're the deputy
warden, sir.
My sister's husband
was arrested selling
counterfeit defense bonds
you furnished him
with in Marseilles.
Dega is a very
common name in Marseilles.
- Santini.
- Yes, sir.
This one goes straight
to route zero.
Take him away.
Wait.
Take him, too.
We try not to separate
old friends here.
Get them to route zero.
Move.
What is route zero?
(EXPLOSIONS)
GUARD: Are those men clear?
You're on the rail!
I don't feel so good.
It goes in the cart.
GUARD: Move along.
You do a lot of talking.
- I do.
- Yeah, stop that.
It passes...
Passes the time.
Get out of my face.
Here, you take
the bigger rock.
If you get into
a fight with him,
I'm not protecting you.
If your wife was here,
you were in Paris
with all that money,
how much would you pay
to get her back?
Everything I have.
How much would she pay
for you?
You're a real optimist.
(EXPLOSION)
Little man.
You need to put
some weight.
You can push harder
than that. Come on.
Trust me, he can't.
Trust me, he has to.
Come on, push it!
GUARD: Clear the charge!
- Push it!
- Pick up the pace.
I have...
I have diarrhea.
What you want me
to do about it?
No, you don't understand.
I lost the money.
(MEN SPEAKING
FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
MAN: What's the holdup?
What the hell are you doing?
(SPEAKS FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
- What?
- Stop shitting around.
- He'll get us all killed.
- You mind your own cart.
That little guy is making more
work for the rest of us.
Mind your own business.
GUARD: Break it up.
Break it up.
What are you doing?
Get up. Get up!
Get up!
(EXPLOSION)
- On your feet.
- I can't.
GUARD: Pick him up.
Come on, pick him up.
Put him in the cart.
(DEGA GROANS)
Back to work.
MAN: Move your cart.
You had one job to do.
You couldn't do it.
My body's in revolt.
Where is it now?
Where do you think?
(CHUCKLES)
I should've known better
than to trust a thief.
I can't steal
what's already mine.
(SCOFFS)
As soon as we get back to the barracks,
you're taking it back.
And you're gonna hold
onto it this time.
I don't care if you have to
sew your ass up to do it.
I'm sorry.
I may have prematurely judged you
with an unworthy degree of suspicion.
Well, don't propose yet.
I just don't like carrying
things in my ass.
He's dead.
- He's dead!
- Shut up, birdie.
Are you stupid or what?
We share his ration.
Here.
You got yourself a boyfriend, huh?
(LAUGHS)
You were in the navy?
What do you think?
I thought maybe it meant
"jailbird."
The swallows.
Stands for hope.
First thing you see
when you reach land.
- PAPILLON: I know.
- Yeah? How come?
You were in the navy?
Eighteen months.
Followed by six
in the brig.
Didn't suit me.
A butterfly.
- So, you're a thief now.
- (CHUCKLES)
Guess that didn't
suit you either.
We should
go sailing sometime.
You got a boat?
Can you get any of that?
Maybe.
Well, let me know then.
Your boyfriend's
got trouble.
(WHISPERS) Give me your money or
you and your friend will die.
Is there trouble?
I was talking
to your bitch.
And now you're
talking to me.
Bitch...
GUARD: Work it out
in the barracks!
Break is over!
Get in line!
Break's over! Form up!
GUARD: Line it up!
Line it up!
- Stop. Stop!
- (WHISTLING AND CHATTER)
Turn around.
Eyes up front. Come on.
You know better than to truck your
ladies through here after a rain storm.
Yeah. Can you help me out?
I'll make it good for you.
Get the girls up here.
Come on.
(WOMEN CHATTERING)
Hey.
Can you hear me?
How much to take me
up the coast?
Don't be stupid.
I'll give you 2,000.
- Guard!
- Don't turn me in, for Christ's sake.
4,000.
GUARD: What's the problem?
Just wanted to know which girl
I should send to repay you.
One that hasn't
caught anything yet.
My boat is on the other
side of the river.
I'll be there
for three more days.
It's 5,000.
You're a goddamn thief.
(LAUGHING)
(FLESH TEARS, SCREAMING)
(YELLING)
(GROANING)
(WHISTLE BLOWING)
The guards are coming.
Don't fucking touch me!
(THUNDER RUMBLING)
I didn't know
it would be like this.
I'll be dead long
before my appeal.
I need to go with you.
That wasn't part
of the deal.
Yes, I realize that,
but I still have to go with you.
You ever sail a boat?
Spent any time at sea?
Yes, I've spent
a number of days at sea.
I was locked in a cage
for most of them.
But I think I understand
the concept well enough.
You can't come
with me, Dega.
(THUNDER RUMBLING)
You should call me Louis.
GUARD: Keep it moving!
Get them in line.
Stand straight!
Down on your knees.
Take off your hats
and cross your arms.
At the moment of execution,
you're all to bow your heads.
A man stabbed two guards,
one of whom died
this morning,
leaving two children without
their father.
And for what?
So he could go on a run
through the jungle.
JULOT: Thank you for coming.
Watch me go to hell!
(PAPILLON COUGHING)
(SPITS)
GUARD: Prisoner ready.
(YELLS)
Keeping you is no benefit.
Destroying you is no loss.
You.
Pick another inmate.
You carry the body.
Go get the boat ready.
(DEGA GROANS)
(GRUNTING)
PAPILLON: He's gone.
It's just flesh and blood.
(BODY DROPS)
Why are you stopping?
What are you doing?
Move.
I said, what the hell
are you doing?
Get up.
Get up, you little worm.
Get your ass up!
(YELLS)
(WHIPPING, YELLING)
GUARD: You little worm.
PAPILLON: Oh, shit.
Oh, shit.
GUARD: Stop.
Hey, stop!
(WHISTLE BLOWS)
Hey!
We've got a runner!
- He's heading north.
- (GUNSHOT)
Papi. Papi?
- Heading north now!
- (GUNFIRE)
(YELLS) Papillon!
(SIREN WAILING)
(WHISTLE BLOWS)
GUARD: Check the tree line!
(PANTING)
(GUNFIRE, BULLETS RICOCHET)
Hey!
(GUNSHOTS CONTINUE)
Take that north side!
- Pick him up.
- (SNIFFLING)
Come on.
You're a good man.
Yeah, I'm a good man
that wants good money.
Look, I don't have it.
Not with me.
But I'm going to make it
worth your while.
I got a lot of money
in Paris.
I'll give you
everything I got.
(RELIEVED SIGH)
(GUNS COCK)
(LAUGHING)
Even if you had the money,
the warden will pay us double.
(WHISPERS) Son of a bitch.
You're lucky
that guard didn't die,
otherwise,
you would have met the guillotine.
Now you'll be transferred to
the island of Saint-Joseph,
where you'll serve a two-year
sentence in solitary confinement.
It's not
rehabilitation.
We know
that's useless.
So, we do our best
to break you.
Strange things
happen there.
Especially to those
who cling to hope.
Because there is no hope
on Saint-Joseph.
Just silence.
GUARD: You heard the warden.
Silence must be observed
at all times.
(FOOTSTEPS THUMPING)
(SIGHS)
(EXHALES)
(RUMBLING, UNLOCKING)
(DOOR UNLOCKS)
Thought you grew wings,
didn't you?
Grab him.
I'll teach you
to be quiet.
(COUGHING)
You make another peep,
you might not survive
your time here.
(COUGHING)
Come on. He's crazy.
Come on. Come on.
Enjoy your next
two years here.
(DOOR LOCKS)
(PANTING)
(HATCH UNLOCKS)
(KNOCKS)
(SNIFFLES)
(WHISPERS) Dega.
(SIGHS)
(DEEP BREATHS)
(HATCH UNLOCKS)
(SIGHS)
GUARD: Hold on.
Need to check that.
GUARD: What is that?
Somebody paying you to bring this shit in,
you son of a bitch?
- (THUD)
- Who's paying you?
Who's paying you,
you son of a bitch?
(THUDDING AND SHOUTING)
(SCREAMING INTENSIFIES,
THEN STOPS)
GUARD 2: Jesus.
I think you killed him.
GUARD 1: Get that body out of
here and clean up the mess.
GUARD 2: What the hell
were you thinking?
No wonder you
haven't broken yet.
How long has it
been going on?
You may speak.
Who sent you
those coconuts?
If you don't fess up,
I'll put you
on half rations.
You're choosing another
man's life over your own.
Put him on half rations.
(DOORS UNLOCK)
(RAPID SWEEPING)
(SOFTLY) I brought you
some soup.
It's got meat in it.
Just tell me his name.
(SOFTLY)
Tell me his name.
Do you think a person knows
when he's going mad?
Or do you think
it's blissful ignorance?
'Cause you're
about to find out.
Put him in darkness for the
remainder of his sentence.
Or the remainder
of his life.
Whichever comes first.
(DOOR LOCKS)
(CHOKES)
Six.
(CLICKS)
(CLANKING)
(RATTLING)
This is a good escape.
(TUMBLERS WHIRRING)
(WHIRRING STOPS)
(UNLOCKING)
Is he still alive?
The years are up.
(GROANING)
WARDEN: I know that some of you at this
very moment are thinking about escape.
Feel free to try
whenever you like.
We'll be happy
to shoot you.
However, should
you avoid that mercy,
there are two guardians
who are always on duty.
The bush, where the best thing that
can happen to you is starvation.
Or you could
choose the sea,
where sharks, too,
are always hungry.
(COUGHING)
(FAINTLY) If you manage to
survive your first attempt,
you'll get two years
in solitary.
Second attempt,
five years in solitary
followed by a life
sentence at Devils Island.
If you commit murder,
you'll be executed.
That's all.
DEGA: Papi.
I wanted
to come sooner,
but I was afraid
you wouldn't wanna see me.
I'm sorry.
It's my fault
you're here.
As you predicted,
my appeal's run into some problems.
But my wife's
doing very well.
She recently
married my lawyer.
Well, to hell
with her then.
You son of a bitch.
I thought you'd gone
simple on me.
(WHISPERS)
That's the idea.
You know, you'd have had
a much easier time
if you'd just given
them my name.
It's not like I didn't
think about it.
I just know how
goddamn delicate you are.
Hmm.
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
(WHISPERS) I fear under similar
circumstances, I would've fared differently.
I don't know
how you made it.
I just got used
to the silence.
If I ever get out,
I'm gonna live
a different kind of life.
This Sunday, the warden will be
showing a film in the courtyard
entertaining some
local politicians.
It'll be loud.
The guards will be doing double duty,
spread very thin.
This is your best chance.
Can you get a boat?
No.
What about Celier?
- Is he still here?
- Unfortunately, yes.
If he can
still get a boat,
do you have enough
money to pay for it?
I might, but then
he'd wanna come with us.
"Us"?
Us.
All right.
But we still need a boat.
You leave now.
Leave!
Get out!
- This man's mad!
- Go!
- Get out!
- He's out of his mind.
No! No, no, no!
No!
- No! Help me!
- He's out of his mind.
Help me!
- Help!
- Here.
Come on, come on.
Calm down, calm down.
Let him go, let him go.
It's okay, it's okay.
Bring me some pills.
Come on. Take one.
Bring me some water.
Swallow.
You'll be okay.
Lights out, 10 minutes.
(KEYS JANGLING)
(LIQUID TRICKLING)
Stop. Relax.
- Relax.
- Get off!
I will never
let you fuck me.
Shh.
(BLOWS KISS)
You will soon,
if you know what's good for you.
Hey. Hey,
I just want to talk.
I'm not a goddamn whore.
That's not what I want.
Yeah, everybody
says that until they do.
Trust me, I don't.
I got a different
proposition.
If you repeat one word of this,
it's not going to be good for you.
I don't want to know, then.
Maybe you do.
Look, I'm putting
something together.
This Sunday.
We got room
for one more.
I have nothing
to offer you.
I need you to
distract that turnkey.
Get him to come in here at a certain time,
keep him occupied.
If I do that,
your plan better work.
It'll work.
It's not going to be easy.
Can you handle yourself?
You were framed
for murder, right?
Well, nobody framed me.
That's Celier.
He's gotten us a boat.
Let's see
the arm. Infected.
Good job.
Papi!
You skinny son of a bitch.
Good to see you.
What'd you do
to your arm?
I had to cut myself
to get in here.
- It still work?
- Yeah, it's nothing.
Don't think about it.
I can still kick your ass.
Can we hurry this up?
I have to get back.
Birdie, can you
shut up for once?
This is Maturette.
He's our fourth.
Oh, yeah?
You know how
to handle yourself?
- Yeah, with a knife.
- All right, take it easy.
Oh, feisty little
one, huh?
- You all set?
- Yeah, I'm set.
I got a guy that's hiding
a boat on the bank.
It's upriver a ways.
From there,
it's a straight shot to the ocean.
But we need
half the money now.
What about you?
When the film starts,
we'll go through the warden's building.
I'll have a key.
We got a plan.
You all right?
No.
I'm not sure
we can trust him.
Look at him.
He's unpredictable.
He's like
a caged animal.
We're all animals
in here, pal.
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
He'll be fine.
He needs the money now.
(MONEY RUSTLES)
Here.
It's the sedatives
they gave me.
Get them
in the guards' coffee.
We'll do the rest.
I have to get back.
Hey.
You're doing good.
- Hey.
- What do we have here, huh?
Go to hell.
Give me those back.
He's going to
fuck up our plan.
He's going to be fine.
What the...
What are you doing, man?
- (FLESH TEARS)
- (MAN SCREAMS)
(WHISTLE BLOWING)
GUARD: All right!
That's enough.
Break it up. Break it up.
He does the
warden's books.
DEGA: Huh...
I'd have figured I'd know
how to throw a punch
considering how often my
father used to beat me.
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
Yours, too?
My parents
are schoolteachers.
See you tonight.
(JAZZ MUSIC PLAYS)
Anisette for the warden.
The best you have.
Just give me the bottle.
(APPLAUSE)
(FILM SOUNDTRACK PLAYS)
(KEYS JANGLING)
There's two or three.
Would you gentlemen
like your coffees freshened?
Yeah, bring it on in.
Compliments
of the warden.
GUARD: Very nice.
(THUDS)
(WHISPERS) Here.
If we kill someone and this goes wrong,
it's the guillotine.
No one dies.
(KEYS JANGLE AND DOOR LOCKS)
- Give me another one of them.
- All right.
(SOUNDTRACK PLAYING)
(ROARS)
Dega, where
are you going?
Dega. The warden. Now.
(MOANING)
(KICKING AND GROANING)
Stop! (SHUSHES)
GUARD: What was that?
I'd better go check.
It's working.
(GROWLING ON SCREEN)
(GRUNTING)
(AUDIENCE APPLAUDS)
Oh, man.
We're too early.
Louis, do you
have a light?
Yes, of course, sir.
(THUNDER CRACKS)
(RAIN POURING)
No.
Okay, go inside.
Everybody, go inside.
- Come on. Come on, darling.
- Fuck.
- That's our way out.
- No, no.
What's he doing?
- (LIGHTNING STRIKES)
- (FILM STOPS PLAYING)
- GUARD: Power's out.
- Oh, fuck.
(SIREN WAILING)
(GUARDS SHOUTING)
Papi, we got to move.
We can't stay here.
We wait for Dega.
Forget about Dega!
He's not reliable,
and you know it.
Let's just go. Come on.
You want to go?
Go.
Are you with me?
Hell, yeah.
Open the gate.
What's wrong with you?
I stole the keys to get us up
to the central walkway.
We can take that
to the guard tower.
As long as the lights stay off,
they won't see us.
- And then we jump?
- You got a better idea?
Come on. Come on.
(SIREN CONTINUES)
Go, go!
I've got the wall.
- You! With me to the south wall.
- Yes, sir!
Yes, we're on lockdown.
Section secured!
Oh, shit.
All right.
Come on. Let's go.
Easy.
Lock it down!
(SIREN CONTINUES)
- (THUDS)
- (GROANS)
- Are you all right?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- Let's go. Come on!
Go, go, go.
Go.
(GRUNTS)
Come on.
Jump!
Come on! They're going to see you!
Come on.
(DEGA GROANS)
- Jump!
- Come on. Jump!
- (BONE SNAPS)
- (DEGA YELLS)
(DEGA SCREAMS)
Shit.
Hey, it's broken.
Leave him.
He's got the money.
(GROANS)
Maturette, help me.
Christ.
All right, come on.
Let's go.
(GUARD YELLING)
Come on. Come on.
Come on.
How much further
to the boat?
- You're slowing us down, Dega.
- Come on.
We've got to move faster.
(GUN COCKS)
(GUNS COCKING)
Don't take another step.
You're not taking me back.
That depends.
Do you have my money?
Hey.
Papi, it's okay.
This is my guy with the boat.
Where's our boat?
It's a ways up the river.
You want me to take you there?
Pay me.
Or fuck you.
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
(WHISPERS)
This is all I have left.
(WHISPERS) Let's
keep that between us.
(GROANS)
Enjoy your freedom.
Fucking jerk.
Fuck!
What kind of shit boat
did you get us?
Shut up, Dega!
You're lucky to be here.
Keep bailing.
- Get it out of the boat.
- I'm trying.
Don't throw it at me,
Dega. God damn it.
- Throw it in the water.
- I'm throwing it at the water!
- Maturette!
- Yes?
Check the tiller.
I got it, I got it.
Papi, this boat can't hold
all of us. You know it.
We need to lighten
the weight.
He's going to die
anyway, Papi.
Nobody needs to die.
Fuck! It fell off!
- Fix the tiller. Fix the tiller!
- It's broken.
- Move.
- (MATURETTE GROANS)
(GRUNTING)
(BAILING CONTINUES)
(SIGHS)
Here, take this.
Take this.
Maturette, help me.
(THUNDER RUMBLES)
(THUNDER CRACKS)
This storm is gonna
sink the boat.
We need to act,
and we need to act now.
Just let me get
the boat ready.
Did you lose your
mind? Huh?
You want to die
because of this guy?
Nobody needs to die.
(THUNDER RUMBLES)
Well, we can't all live.
Dega, he's dead weight.
How much money you have?
He doesn't have any money.
He doesn't have any money?
You hear that, Maturette?
They've been lying to us.
You want to die for him?
That makes it two against one, Papi.
Step aside.
No need to do anything.
Step aside, Papi!
I'm not going to
die for that guy.
Last chance, Papi.
Step aside!
I don't know about you.
I'm going home!
(GROWLING)
(THUNDER RUMBLES)
(GRUNTING)
Shit.
(GASPS)
(GASPING)
Dega.
Stop! Stop!
(YELLS)
PAPILLON: Enough.
That's enough.
Enough.
(BODY THUDS)
(SHUDDERING)
(GRUNTING)
(GASPS)
(BIRDS CHIRPING)
(CHILDREN GIGGLE)
Welcome.
I was traveling
with two other men.
They're being cared for.
Where are we?
This is Colombia.
We know where
you've come from.
But you need
only repent.
Allow God back
into your life,
and you'll be forgiven.
You should go
and wash yourself.
Then come
and pray with us.
We need to keep moving.
They know where
we came from.
Our deal is done.
I told you we
couldn't trust him.
I'm leaving.
With or without you.
Good luck.
Papi, we made it!
Papi, it's
paradise here.
Yeah, but it's not home.
Not for me, anyway.
Good luck, Maturette.
(MOTOR WHIRRING)
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATION)
We're leaving.
Now!
(DEGA GROANS)
Come on.
MATURETTE: Papi!
Maturette!
(GROANS)
NUN: Repent!
If you are truly sorry
for what you have done,
then you have
nothing to fear!
God will watch
over you.
You came back.
(DOOR UNLOCKS AND CREAKS)
Come on, Papi.
I had to come
and see this for myself.
Few men survive
five years in solitary.
What were you living for?
'Cause I don't think you're going
to find it where you're going.
Devils Island.
Let me out!
(DISTRESSED VOICES ECHO)
Now, what's the son of two schoolteachers
doing in a place like this?
Well,
what do you think?
I've had five years
to work on it.
The warden wasn't very happy
with my disobedience,
so he sent me straight
here to Devils Island.
(TAPS POT)
Let's get some
food in you.
Rise and shine.
Come on.
There's work to be done.
(WATER SPLASHES)
(YELLING IN DISTANCE)
Let me out!
Can we get to the ocean?
DEGA: I know what
you're thinking.
But even if you
survive the fall,
you'll never
survive the ocean.
(GROANS)
- It's all about the waves.
- What?
What are you
talking about?
What do you think
I'm talking about?
Oh, go back to bed.
That's suicide, not escape.
No, listen.
All we need to do is build a
raft and get it to the ocean.
The tide will take us
straight to the mainland.
Just come and see.
Come and see.
PAPILLON: See? We ride
the current to freedom.
(DEGA GROANS)
(THUDS)
(DEGA PANTS)
I'm a little concerned about your
ability to protect me right now.
Don't worry.
The fall will probably kill us.
Let's tie
these together.
I need to stay.
What are you
talking about?
I need to stay.
For the same reason
you have to go.
I belong here.
It's okay.
It's good.
Come on, now, you don't want to
waste any more time.
(SNIFFLES)
(GRUNTS)
(DISTANTLY) Louis!
Louis!
I made it, you
dirty little forger!
(WHOOPS)
(BOTH WHOOPING)
(SNIFFLES)
AIR HOSTESS: This is for you.
WOMAN: Thank you.
Sir? Your water.
- Thank you.
- You're welcome.
MAN: I'm surprised
you risked coming back.
I'd read the statute
of limitations.
You're still a wanted man.
I won't be here long.
My home is Venezuela now.
But it's important
that my memoir
be published here,
in France.
My wife convinced me
to write it all down
while I'm still young
enough to remember.
So, is this
really your story?
It's the story
of a lot of men.